hi everybody how is everyone doing
tonight
nice my name is Steven if you don't know
me and I'm Jin zone thank you all for
coming it's a rainy out Reno and cold so
but thanks for coming tonight it's a
lovely teaching if you don't know I am
the manager of three jewels for those
that do know we just opened the new
center and it's really beautiful you
should all come and it wouldn't be what
it does without you and all of teachings
and especially Geshe Michael for making
it all happen it wouldn't even exist
without that so thank you gosh LA and
it's been open 22 years for some of you
you've been there from the start you
know what it was it was a small tea shop
and book store and now it's grown into
this beautiful studio that offers eight
classes a day we have 4,000 students
coming we started our first meditation
teacher training last year we're doing
our first yoga teacher training I like
we have a lot of people in the audience
yeah we did a retreat last year we're
doing another one in March and it just
keeps growing and growing so it's really
beautiful please come visit the new
space and we also have more information
about a CI the classes that we teach at
three jewels a CI classes have been
going on in New York since Gachet
michael founded Asian classics Institute
and has over 18 courses for seven years
he taught us here and now he's teaching
even more
in mostly in Arizona and throughout the
world but during his time when he was
here in New York he studied for over 25
years with Ken Rinpoche Lopes on tartan
in at Russia gambling and he taught many
of us I see here in in in this room so
and he had Geshe Michael as he was
teaching us today at the Diamond Club he
talked about how Ken Rinpoche had him
used the diamond cutter Sutra to in his
business which he did for several years
at Andy and international which he grew
from a 50,000 investment into I think
I'll get it right this time a 50,000
loan into two hundred million dollars in
sales so that's using the diamond cutter
Sutra which tonight is what we're
studying and it's a commentary by kamila
Sheila which is really extraordinary as
Jensen will be teaching more on this
Thursday three jewels and and it's
really beautiful how it goes into
different meditations that he has
designed based on Camilla Sheila's
commentaries so it brings these
beautiful in-depth messages to us in
real life and that's what's you can
apply it in your daily life and that's
really great and what's happening now is
that that is a course that there'll be
another part coming up in up to a
preliminary
but that's the other come with Sheila
that we'll be covering and currently
Geshe Michael is also putting together
with Asian classics Institute
they're like developing a new meditation
training and
a CI is like it keeps growing and I just
want to take a moment to thank the ACI
president Jigme venerable Jigme and Tim
[Applause]
for for helping the new programs I guess
you Michael is developing to making them
happen really quickly and they'll tell
you later where they're happening at the
end of the year but in this curriculum
is going to be really innovative and a
very comprehensive meditation program
and ACI will teach hopefully here in New
York with these new trainings and we can
have a place that we can go stop by and
soon also getting Michael will be
traveling so we still have him in New
York right we're not saying that today
okay sorry
for one not so but anyway I really want
to welcome guess you Michael back home
in New York City and hopefully he will
come again next year to teach us come
with Sheila part five so thank you thank
you everybody Michael
[Applause]
[Music]
you
[Applause]
[Music]
hey you guys are gonna give me trouble
cuz half a you didn't come last night
raise your hands if you didn't come last
night yeah see ya okay okay it's because
of them I have to teach the pen okay not
that I want to teach the pen I don't
want to teach the pain okay Francis you
ready okay he's my helper I'm sorry to
put you other guys through this it's not
fair I know anyway okay just don't get
nervous just answer don't think about it
okay what's this thing yeah okay if a
dog came in here and downing her puppy
dog and I wave it in front of the dog
what would they do with it yeah they all
chewing it does the dog see this as a
pen does the human see this as a chew
toy who's right now yeah Francis they
learned it only took like five years
okay if I put the thing here I don't
call it a penny right if I put this
thing here and then all the dogs go out
of the room and all the humans go out of
the room there's nobody left then at
that time is it a pen or is it a chew
toy
good now Francis I didn't prepare you
for this but what do we call that in
Buddhism what's the name for that don't
cheat grandma ah emptiness okay so
forget what you ever heard about
emptiness okay it's not like you close
your eyes and everything's black okay
that's not gonna make you successful or
happy okay and it's not that you close
your eyes and you just watch thoughts
come and go because that also won't make
you happy my Lama used to say if that
was the goal of emptiness then you could
just buy a six-pack of beer and drink it
fast and you could see emptiness okay so
it's not uh it's not that you close your
eyes and you try to think about nothing
okay then the worst version of emptiness
which is wrong is
it means that nothing's right or
nothing's wrong okay so that's also
obviously completely crazy you know so
or the idea that you should try to think
about nothing when you meditate because
actually that does have a karmic result
if you you know just sit in the corner
and you stare at the wall and you watch
your thoughts and you watch them fade
into nothing it does have an effect it's
in the scriptures you become forgetful
and you leave your keys and your cell
phone and you wander around the house
like this then okay so those are not
emptiness emptiness as Francis pointed
out is when this thing is here and all
the dogs are gone and all the people are
gone then this is emptiness okay and
it's like a white movie screen think of
it like a white movie screen okay
Francis you ready
gessie Michael comes back in the room he
walks up to this thing he looks down and
it becomes one yeah it becomes a pen
again okay which Oh
what if the dog walked in before me and
they go what does it become chew toy
okay which proves I'll ask you is the
pen coming from the pen or is the pen
coming from me somehow yeah I must be
coming from me because otherwise I would
start to slobber when I come up here
okay and I don't I mean not usually so
so we can say that it's coming from me
now there's an important part if you're
gonna learn it right we teach how to
teach the pen at our College there's
eighteen steps to teaching the pen and
at this point if you have time right if
you're not in a hurry you can say well
if I just close my eyes and I wish very
hard okay if it's coming from me which
nobody disagreed right if it's coming
from me can I just hold it in my hand
and close my eyes and can I wish that it
was something else can I think
positively and visualized very strongly
that this is a diamond and not a pen
then since it's coming from me
will it become a diamond I mean we can
try but it doesn't work and you know
depends on what country you're in but
it's the same for mantra Joe you know
you can do all money baby who or any
kind of mantra you can also do a prayer
but it won't it won't work it won't
become a diamond okay and you know that
if things became if things became things
because you wanted them to become things
then everybody would have what they want
so we say positive thinking doesn't work
I'm sorry okay
you can positive think all you want you
know I don't want cancer and then you
get cancer and it doesn't stop it okay
so it is coming from me but something's
forcing it to come from me there's
something in my mind that forces me to
see a pen okay when I open when I come
up on the stage there's something in my
mind buddhism calls it see jones we call
it a mental karmic Yalie see same thing
it's coming from a seed in your mind so
we all have seeds in our minds and when
I come up on the stage and I get about
here and I look at it in that moment a
seed opens in my mind okay
and then it produces a little picture of
a pen which is about this big and it's
made of light okay it's it's a luminous
picture and that picture comes out of
your mind and it goes on these pieces
okay if I have a seed in my mind for pen
I will see a pen if I have a seat in my
mind for a chew toy I will see chew toy
so the seeds run everything in your life
and you don't know because they open at
the rate of do you know 65 per second
six
five per second a good movie is a video
on the internet is 24 frames I think per
second but you have frames for smell
taste touch okay your frames are 65
seats per second or opening so you don't
notice that the world is a bunch of
photographs moving very fast and we're
going to talk about it today if we get
time because there's a secret
presentation of the diamond cutter Sutra
in the collar chakra okay which it's not
secret after tonight if we have time
we'll do that but so these are coming
out of your mind very fast and they are
making your life they are making your
world okay and the cool thing is and
what I what we like to teach people we
teach all over the world we teach a
thing called diamond cutter Institute
and you know we don't try to make people
Buddhists you know like I did for a
while in New York when I was in New York
I was trying to make everybody Buddhist
then I realize it doesn't really matter
you know if they learn about seeds and
if they use them and it makes them happy
and successful then let them be whatever
their parents were I don't care you know
people ask me what do you have on your
altar I have a picture of Jimi Hendrix
okay like it doesn't matter who you put
on the wall you know it doesn't really
matter if I can teach you something
today that will make the rest of your
life very happy and very successful then
I don't care you know what's your
religion or what country you're from so
we had this idea let's take these
principles I just go to different
countries and don't tell people it's
Buddhist and just teach them the
principles about how to plant seeds
because if I can learn to plant the
seeds I want in my mind then I can
design 2,000 the rest of 2018 you see
that
I can design each part of 2018 here
and then it's it's a really fun okay if
you learn how to do it and I encourage
you to do a small experiment in your own
life okay after tonight I'll teach you
how to plant a seed and then you don't
have to believe me
and what I like to tell people in when
we travel like we're going to India
tomorrow right and we're teaching
hardcore Hindus and Jains and then after
that we go to Kazakhstan and we teach
hardcore Muslim people and then after
that we go to Vienna and teach half
Catholic half process
oh and Instanbul so you know I don't
care where you're from I don't care what
your parents did but if I can teach you
a way to design next year and you do a
small experiment you know if if I say it
worked for me
you know I say today we had a what do
you call we had a VIP talk today and I
don't know I don't like VIP talks
because I have to talk and I don't get
to eat and they're all they're all
eating this really nice lunch you know
I'm like but I said there are five goals
that we noticed people want in their
life number one is financial freedom so
I don't care about money you know these
guys know I lived in a six by six room
for 25 years they know they were there I
don't care about money I don't need
money and I don't really want money but
I would like to have freedom from money
I don't want to be tied down to money I
I want money to just come and I don't
have to think about it you know
and then I wanted to just be automatic
so that's the first thing that would be
nice
then you free half your mind half your
mind is freed from worrying about money
and that's very nice okay so I I did
that and we started a business with
alone fifty thousand and it got to two
hundred fifty million
and it was sold to Warren Buffett in
2009 then now we have a new company how
old eight seven eight years yeah and the
money just comes it's it's weird it's
just cool you know so try it just give
it a try okay if you hear about me
talking like that and you don't try it
this week then there's something wrong
with you okay now if you choose to work
like a slave you know and get old empire
and there's a better way then you're
just kind of crazy okay so I'll teach
you how to plant a seed okay second
thing I think it's one thing to have
money but it's a beautiful thing to have
a partner beautiful partner a beautiful
family beautiful friends beautiful
business partners I'd like to introduce
Scott a Noreen would you stand up yeah
so we we have our company together John
Foley sometimes houses please yeah if
you ever saw Top Gun the guy going in
the plane like this it's not Tom Cruise
it's him he was in the Blue Angels and
he he did the he did some of the flying
for that movie so anyway we give talks
together sometimes so anyway you know if
you hear about it second goal would be
have a beautiful relationship third goal
I think is to have good health have
energy don't be tired all the time
you know be able to do headstand swears
Lady Ruth she's hiding oh hi she's my
real first yoga teacher I'd like to
thank her
lady Ruslan
if you have seized yoga makes you strong
and healthy and you could be an old man
and still have fun if you don't have
seeds okay and you do the same yoga you
will hurt your neck okay seriously it's
all it's good to have a the best yoga
teacher in the world but it also helps
to have seeds okay but we'll talk about
that so health then I think we all want
to have mental peace you know like it's
nice to be successful but there are many
unhappy successful people Robin Williams
I think I always think of him he has all
the money in the world he has beautiful
family and he can also pay a doctor to
to quietly give him a shot if he wants
to die but he hung himself with his belt
in his bedroom because he's so unhappy
you see I mean so I would like to be
happy I would like to have a meditative
state of mind and when I was young which
was 100 1800s no there was an attitude
either you meditate or you do business
you see either you have a spiritual life
and you quit working or you work and you
don't have a spiritual life this was the
attitude when I was younger and I think
now part of what we want to help people
reach is where you have a real active
business life you have a you know a
career and and you are doing something
fun for society you're helping people
with producing something or making
something or you know you do something
real in the world and at the same time
you have a real meditative practice at
home and in your own mind so somehow
you're what's their word in Chinese
Jinjin sir what's the businessman who
knows sagen soon yeah
a businessperson who also knows the
classics and lives them okay
that's an old Confucian ideal you know
and and I would like to see that I would
like I think that would be beautiful you
know we were at the New World Bank in
Beijing and we gave a presentation for
some of the directors and when in
December and they really liked this idea
of training people just not to be just
business people but to have some kind of
inner life some kind of beautiful inner
life at the same time and it and they're
very excited about it and and it used to
be like that right so anyway we're
working on that that would be a goal and
then we talked about it today in the VIP
luncheon if I get all those things right
if I like make I don't know what do you
call it there's a bad word for it enough
money to tell the world something and
money is just coming in and then if my
house is really good I have beautiful
relationships at work and at home and my
inside life is very rich and very
peaceful right but everyone around me is
unhappy and everyone around me is
nervous and everyone around me has
financial problems and then it's not fun
you see you're okay you have everything
you want you know how to plant a scene
in your mind but other people around you
don't so you have to sit on the bus next
to people suffering you have to see
members of your family suffering and
it's not fun you see so for me
and in Buddhism we say to to share it
with other people would be happiness you
see if I can teach you something it's
you know if I gave you right now ten
thousand dollars right you would thank
me you'd be all excited and but if I
taught you a way to make ten thousand
dollars every day what do you call it
don't give a man a fish teach him to
fish
we're all vegetarian so you know teach
someone how to do it themselves
then that's the greatest gift and and
when you give it to people you feel
happy all the time because the next time
you see them I was in Shanghai last year
and this guy was waiting at the door for
me
when I finished the talk I left the room
you know and he was I I know this kind
of person there like this I got to talk
to you I gotta talk to you I'm like I'm
busy I'm busy he's no no I gotta talk to
you you know I'm like I'm sorry I really
don't have time my whole life is booked
you know tonight
okay just talk to me in the elevator
just talk me to me any other man I'm
like okay then I got Scott on one side
in case the guys like gets if he won't
stop talking Scott's like yes
and so he's on one side he's on this
side the the other guys over here he
says I came to hear talk last year I
said thank you you know and I came this
year yeah okay what but something's
wrong I said what's wrong he says I
didn't get what I wanted you know I said
did you do the forest dance right now I
have to teach you the four steps let's
just do this four steps real fast okay
four people want you got $100 anybody
$100 there's a contest okay I'm gonna do
this lady
do you mind help me
one time I my staff went to give a
tongue oh you got a diamond pin one time
one time my staff gave it talked to a
thousand people and then I gave a talk
the next night and we picked the same
lady yeah come on
okay very quick okay we're just gonna
review the four steps step number one
decide what you want I gave you five
classical choices but you can choose
something else there was a lady in
Singapore she says I want to be the
swimming champion of Singapore I'm like
okay she's now the swimming champion of
Singapore really what do you call that
dancing underwater thing what's it
called synchronized swimming she's the
Asian metals champion that was her do
you choose what you want okay that's the
first job if you don't know what you
want choose that number one I want to
know what I want okay number two you
must have a karmic partner okay
this system of Lord Buddha doesn't work
without a karmic partner it's like I
like to say it's like playing basketball
without a floor you know it's not gonna
work out so you need to have a karmic
partner and that's step number two they
should want something similar to what
you want you know so if you want a
boyfriend don't pick someone who wants
money or something like that I gave this
talk in Detroit and this young man came
in the second day and he's like jumping
up and down and he says I found her I
found her I said what what did you find
I found her you know she's perfect you
know I said what who isn't she's poor
she's sick and she's old and he's all
excited you know because he can get good
health money and what's the other one a
partner at the same time so anyway yeah
try to find somebody like that okay
that's the second thing third thing
helped them for one hour every week to
get what they want
helped them for every for one hour every
week to get what they want
okay and I don't mean you have to give
people money it's it's kind of more
useful if you teach them how to make
money right it's kind of more useful to
to teach them a skill that's what we do
with the refugees 31 years dr. Chilton
you have to stand up yes he helped
started 31 years ago and they've been
typing ancient books for money for 31
years
and there's like I think 20,000 books
online for free okay so you know find
somebody who needs something okay so
we're gonna just practice this is not
the real thing but maybe it is people
ask me why I keep giving away money
every night it's not a demonstration
okay I depend on it for my income I'm
not kidding you think I'm kidding okay
so what's your name Jen's gonna hold up
her hand then I'm gonna do step number
three okay I put the money in her hand
and I close her hand
now watch one two er Sun Bing okay ding
means I just created a seed in my mind
okay why who saw my hand open yeah I saw
it so karma is recording you okay
in your mind when you see yourself do
something you see it has to be recorded
by your mind your mind is a video camera
then everything you say everything you
do and everything you think is recorded
in your mind I did a three-year silent
retreat in one cabin a small room for
three years in the desert it was hard
and I found out that everything you ever
saw in your life is still in there
so I used to play movies sometimes
I have played my favorite movies alright
so I wasn't meditating the whole time I
have to confess so that's the first
three steps okay now if you played a
karma it it might take a thousand years
to open okay that's the problem you see
if karma opens in 24 hours everyone will
be a nice person
you know if I give her $100 and tomorrow
I have a thousand then everybody would
figure it out the problem is there's a
long time delay you see there's a very
long time today it can be a year it can
be ten years you know so people don't
get faith in the system because it takes
so long to get your interest back you
see so you have to know step number four
she's dumped at your heart to heart talk
means you have to put prana on the seat
okay you have to put Chi on the scene
the way you put Chi on a scene if you
think about it okay because long center
but cheaper Bob Chilton knows
prana and the thought travel in tandem
thought is the horse prana is the rider
and if I think about giving her money
tonight if I think about it tonight
before I go to bed then the prana the
Chi goes to the Karma and it heats it up
and it opens fast it'll open I don't
know I gave a talk in Singapore and I
and Malaysia and Indonesia and I gave
away 10 $100 bills in ten nine then I
came home and my jing-mei where are you
anyway she's my secretary for 25 years
sometimes she puts mail on my yeah thank
you
sometimes she'll put the mail on my desk
you know I get home I open the mail over
the first letter I open there's $10,000
chick okay from unexpected just a gift
from somebody so it's a I gave away
1,000 normally the return is about ten
times okay
no it is it's really about I'm I'm
designed tonight a thousand dollars okay
and it's very frustrating for me to give
these talks in fact do you know
spiritual gangster it's a yoga clothing
company they're in Bloomington's
recently and a friend of mine started
the company and and I go to have lunch
with him sometimes in Phoenix he's from
Phoenix and so I'll sit down with him
and he'll say geshe-la
thank you so much you know he's your
friend too he'll say thank you so much
and I'm wealthy now it's all because of
what you taught me
and he says but something disturbs me
and I'm like what he says how come
people right around you don't use it you
know and I'm like I don't know I don't
know why they don't use it you know and
and he says I use it every day and
that's why I'm in bloomingdales you know
like he started with three t-shirts or
something and now he's the I think he's
the biggest yoga clothing company in
America okay
and anyway try it okay don't be don't be
stubborn okay I don't know why I have to
see stubborn people
that's an old DC I joke because
everything's a mirror right so anyway
okay so anyway step number four before
you go to bed at night
think about the good things you did okay
for other people and we were talking
today somebody asked me is that pride
because a lot of us we feel
uncomfortable to think about good things
we did and we think oh I have pride okay
I'll tell you what pride is pride is I'm
the best money giveaway in New York
nobody can give away money like me not
even John Foley cannot give away money
like
you know that's prime and that's a bad
seed okay you will have bad result okay
happiness rejoice we call coffee
meditation it's like I'm so happy I'm
making money with a new system you know
by helping other people this is cool
this is really nice you know and I'm so
happy I helped this lady Jen she seems
happy she's gonna take her friend out to
dinner afterwards right and I'm just
happy that she had a nice smile and it's
fun okay so have fun with it okay
that's a very powerful Karma fun is a
very powerful Karma okay now we aren't
talking about the four steps we're
talking about the guy in Shanghai who is
nervous at the door do you remember that
he's like I didn't work you know I'm
like oh boy I said okay in my mind I'm
like let's check and see if he did the
four steps then I was in the diamond
business in New York for 19 years and
Chen zom said a few years it's like ten
thousand trips on the bus from how 19
years in the diamond business and I my
boss he taught me how we I did
negotiations all day with diamond
sellers and my job is to you know see if
they're telling the truth or not and my
boss taught me the trick you know one is
a person who is about to lie will look
down you know you say how much this time
and cost I'll say $2,000 you know and
then you say I don't think so
and I say yeah you're right it's really
1,500 you see so if they look down they
they're gonna lie okay
second thing they'll move something on
the table just before they lie don't
move a pencil or they'll reach for
something on the table in their
movements so I'm watching this guy's
eyes you know I said did you do the four
steps he said he didn't get what he want
did you do the four steps he's like yes
I'm like dang he's not lying
I said I'm sorry I said did you do
number one and look at his eyes and he's
like yes and I said well what did you do
for number one he said well I chose to
make ten million dollars he was offended
that I didn't remember his goal because
I'd meet 20 thousand people every year
we teach 20,000 people every year and he
was a very offended that I didn't
remember that he wanted ten million
dollars so then I say okay did you pick
a karmic partner I'm doing right now
okay he's like yes then I'm like who was
it and he says oh my friend he wants to
start an export business same business
and I helped you know I said did you
help him he goes yes I helped him you
know I'm like dang then I said so every
night before he went to bed
did you think about the kind pain you
did for this other person yeah I said no
you didn't he said oh you know I said
you're doing good he said yeah I didn't
do it every night you know I did
sometimes I didn't this is so typical in
the whole world you're gonna do the same
thing tonight you'll say I'll do it
tomorrow and then you won't get anything
and you'll blame me okay so tonight you
know I checked his eyes and he's like
yeah I said I said you didn't do number
four and he said you're right I didn't
do number four you know cuz I didn't
feel comfortable to be happy about my
own goodness okay so don't do that okay
that's stupid
it's not pride okay it's not pride pride
is you tell all your friends
Oh last night I'm Jen dark I gave her
hundred dollars nice-lookin a good
person you know that's pride okay this
is not pride just quietly before you
sleep think I did something good for
another person okay it's all private
it's all quiet you don't tell anybody
okay then I told him that's why you
didn't get with you that's why you
didn't get anything you know and then he
got really angry he got really no Kenny
said I didn't say that I said you just
told me the reason we're talking is you
say
you didn't get what you want yeah I
didn't get what I want but I didn't say
I didn't get anything you know I said
well what did you get
he said I only got eight million dollars
then I'm like - Scott you know Scott's
on this side I'm like I wish I had this
guy's problem so he was complaining then
as a teacher okay you know from our
teacher you have to be really tough on
students you know so I look at him like
shocked you know
you lost two million dollars because
you're too lazy to be happy every night
you know I screamed at him then this
year I met him in the elevator again he
this time he's waiting in the elevator
and he's like I got it I didn't I got
ten million you know and I'm he got it
the second year he got ten okay so step
number four is important okay step
number four now you haven't know how to
plant a seed okay first step decide what
you want and second step find a county
partner third step help them one hour
every week one hour every week if you
tell me you don't have one hour every
week to help another person okay go work
80 hours you know go work 80 hours to
tell you're too old to do it you know
okay I agree
you know don't work 79 hours and give
the guy one hour work 80 hours you know
and work work work okay and tell you're
too tired to work okay it's like crazy
don't tell me you don't have one hour to
make 200 million dollars you know just
do it okay just try it okay all right
now my two husbands ready okay this is a
skit we did last night I'm sorry you
guys the biochar people came already
come we got to be the same I think who's
number one okay good all right this is a
very fast kid I'm sorry if you were here
last night it's not my fault these
people just came tonight okay
and then we'll get to the diamond cutter
suitor okay lexan you ready so okay I'm
regular working woman in America I have
kids I have a husband you know in the
old days the labor was divided the the
wife did the cooking and the wash the
kids and the husband made the money now
the division is different the wife does
the cooking watch the kid and make the
money and the television the the husband
watches television okay this is the new
way so you know so I have two kids
Chinni not will you be one of my kids
okay so these are my two kids okay loon
Sean you were a kid yesterday okay
so these are my two kids and my boss
told me I had to come in early on
Thursday or something okay and I told my
kids to get ready they mom has to go an
hour early tomorrow please be ready to
go to school an hour early and then you
know the story you're gonna do it you're
supposed to be jumping on the bed just
do a little bit okay that's not bad then
they were jumping on the bed they
weren't ready and I say you're the
stupidest kids in New York or in Powell
okay
like I get mad at them and I say who
heard me yeah I did and that plants a
karma okay you got a you got a notice
that okay your mind is a tape recorder
and when you say something that plants a
karma it makes an impression on your
mind when you hear yourself say you are
the stupidest kids in where are you from
New Jersey right the other stupidest
kids in New Jersey and then a lot of
anyway then that makes an impression on
your mind and then in about I don't know
a couple hours that becomes a son scar
that's planted in the mind it becomes a
karmic seed okay
in about two hours something like that
so it makes a impression literally it
makes an impression on your mind okay so
I have this seed now in my mind because
of my too bad
kids you're not so bad she's okay sorry
God so now next week I come home from
work I'm tired you know I picked up the
kids the bad kids and I picked up
groceries and and I'm exhausted because
I worked all day because the husband's
watching the internet right now and may
it never happened to you so then but I'm
thinking on the way home I'm wondering
why do I have this husband anyway
because he doesn't do anything oh but he
gives me in good hugs good hugs is worth
a lot okay it's better than sitting by
yourself and eating dinner or something
okay
so I come home I opened the door I
opened my arms and then the husband
yells at me okay then what's the first
thing you sing I did anything I just
opened you you say some bad words
probably I just opened the door and he
he said bad things to me you know and I
didn't I didn't do anything it's like
your friends are there and you say I
write I said I don't know what's wrong
with him you know I didn't do anything
he's yelling at me okay
then what's the second thing you get
upset right
what's human nature I'm not stupid
you're stupid who hurt me yeah I did and
then I plant a new scene in my mind what
happens next week with the kids they're
bad why the seat opens garden this
Buddhism calls the cycle son sorry okay
now we have to talk real fast about them
then we'll go to the diamond cutter
seeker and I'm sorry to repeat from last
night it's not my fault it's the people
who didn't come last night so why do I
have two husbands in the kitchen okay
you have to understand this has been
number one okay Tim he by the way he's
also in charge with Jigme for ACN I'd
like to thank him
and they do lots of retreats every year
in different countries and different
places Thailand Mexico Diamond Mountain
so you know come sometime talk to him
I think he's gonna pitch it later so
this husband is here because I didn't
he's I didn't do anything husband okay
got it
this one just yelled at me I didn't do
anything all right this husband Scott
husband number two he comes from me okay
got it
he's coming out of my seat what see then
I planted with the two bad kids okay
that put a scene in my mind and then
that's he'd open like the seed for the
pen open right Francis when Geshe
Michael walk up on the stage that seed
open and a pen that became a pen okay
then when I walk in the door that seed
opens and my husband yells at me so
there are two husbands here this one do
you remember from last night he's called
mister I didn't do anything
okay he's I didn't do anything okay
that's the first one second one is
coming from my seats okay now one of
them exists wasn't one of them doesn't
exist which is which yeah number one
which is Tim he doesn't really exist
okay
he's not my phone okay then this husband
he is my phone okay he's the one that
came from yelling at my kids okay got it
now what is emptiness it's worth $50 if
someone gives me no you don't count he
cleaned out my pocket yesterday
huh what too easy huh
you said wait say it again yeah that one
is emptiness okay why he give me three
reasons why and it's really it goes up
to 100 you got 50 already know there's
three things about him no come on let
him okay forget it 50 Buddha said Buddha
said that one cannot exist never existed
in the past and will never exist in the
future
totally impossible okay Buddha said it
that way three things you know isn't
there now wasn't there yesterday will
never be there tomorrow and and that
fact that you never met a person in your
life who's not coming from you okay you
never met a person in your life who's
not coming from you okay
that's emptiness that's what Buddha's
call emptiness okay so forget everything
you ever heard about emptiness okay
that's real emptiness why because it can
help you to create a perfect partner
okay
real emptiness is really useful okay
real emptiness
what do you call Kong Ching gender
gender function is a really useful okay
because then you can make a perfect
partner okay you can change your partner
without talking to him fix your seeds
here with your kids and then suddenly he
becomes a nice person and you don't have
to negotiate with him okay it's very
useful if you're married okay all right
you husband's gonna hope by the way this
husband exists and it's worth fifty
dollars if somebody can tell me the
Buddhist word for the second husband
yeah it's not you guys
he's got John Tim's got you huh
Karma's close you're getting close it's
the opposite it's the opposite of the
coin of emptiness
huh who's that bad dependent 50 bucks
okay see me afterwards okay there's a
long word in Buddhism it's called
dependent origination okay he he comes
because of my seat
that's called dependent origination the
opposite of that is Tim whose emptiness
and their flip side of the same coin
okay this one comes from my how I
treated people yesterday that's called
in in Buddhism dependent dependent
origination and this one was never there
okay that's called emptiness okay so I
owe 50 and 50 okay meet me afterwards if
you don't meet me I'm I'm not
responsible
okay all right thank you okay
now we're caught up to today okay and I
apologize again to people who were here
yesterday but now you remember it for
two days instead of one day okay we were
going through the diamond cutter Sutra
Jing hunting the last page has a poem on
it so the Buddha you know went out with
a poem by the way we're using the big
reading okay you should have a big
reading if you don't have a big reading
raise your hand can someone bring them a
big reading okay keep your hand up or
they don't know who you are unless you
didn't take a shower okay
sorry it's coming so we're going through
this reading okay
and this is the explanation of the poem
at the end of the diamond cutter Sutra
which is so holy that it became a mantra
in in Tibet and you can learn a common
rodriram even gilma seviche with the
mineral not intended a surgeon and a
data
what's the Sanskrit terracotta middle
deep food butum cha cha everyone rush WM
Sanskrit I'm very famous okay you should
learn it if you're a Buddhist okay
it's a good poem inside that poem
anybody with their hand up is gonna get
everything inside that pump there are
nine messages okay there are nine
different messages inside the pump we
did half of them yesterday and we're
gonna do the other half tonight okay
so you have to stay until I finish one
more here
Hannibal one more here Danielle okay
here we go
and we're on page five and we're on
number five okay so we covered already
somebody tell me the first one I'm not
offering any money you should know star
okay life is like a star what's the
second one cataract the problem with
your eye like a scratch on your eye
what's the third one
butter lamp
Carmen rubbing mama the guma Maya Maya
illusion okay we're in the middle of the
fourth one we're on a pretty good track
to finish unless geshe-la gets
distracted with some story okay so we're
in the middle of explaining the meaning
of illusion okay if someone can give me
the one word for illusion I'm sorry I
don't usually bribe people but it seems
to work in New York
no one English word for Maya who said
discovers it
okay hundred meet me afterwards
discrepancy between what you see what
what's appearing to you and what you
think you see okay a discrepancy there's
a difference between the way it looks
and the way it really is in the kitchen
example see if I get you used to money
your answer in the kitchen example it
looks like the husband yelled for no
reason at all okay but the reality is
he's coming from you he's yelling
because you yelled at the kids last week
okay
that's illusion that's classical
Buddhist illusion don't think it's
anything else Maya's nothing else
there's no other meaning of Maya
my amines discrepancy between what you
think you see and what's really there
okay if you think you see a husband
yelling at you that's not coming from
you you can get angry okay then it's
possible to get angry if you realize
there's no such husband and that's what
emptiness then you cannot get angry you
can get angry at one person who yourself
got it
okay emptiness is useful okay a person
who understands emptiness should be free
from anger for the rest of their life in
theory okay but Joshi Michael can tell
you it sometimes breaks down in a few
moments okay if your partner really
yells at you you know somebody pushes
you in the subway you suddenly forget
all your Buddhism you know okay and I'm
good at that okay so anyway we're in the
middle of Maya Maya means discrepancy
between what you see and what's really
there okay it looks like the husband
decided to yell at you for no reason but
the reality is he's coming from you okay
and that's illusion that's the meaning
of illusion so don't think any weird
thing you know all the weird things
about Buddhism are weird they're not
correct okay they're all stupid okay
somebody explains that to you just yell
at yourself in the bathroom okay all
right page five number five you have
three options when you're in the kitchen
with the husband and he's screaming okay
you have three options he's yelling at
you okay option number one no one ever
taught you the pen Francis was
unavailable that day and he didn't teach
you the pen he's like in the gang he's
in the second grade he's gonna be scary
later okay you gotta be careful he'll be
lecturing you Auri
if he's not already so
there's people who never heard anyone
talk about how you plant things in your
own mind there's a lot of people like
eight seven point nine nine nine million
in New York okay a lot of people just
never heard about it okay
they're they have no chance to have real
happiness in this life okay they will
get angry at every person who yells at
them or they will think they should get
angry okay even if they don't get angry
they'll think they were right you see so
that's first choice person who never
heard about emptiness we say that person
has very little chance of really
overcoming anger in their lifetime they
will always be about as angry as they
were when they were a kid you know maybe
they were a nice kid
but that they will not improve that way
okay second kind you walked in the
kitchen your husband yelled at you you
forgot about this talk which is gonna
happen after tomorrow and then you
called them stupid and then you went to
the I don't know you went to change your
clothes and you suddenly ten minutes
later you realize you just planted some
bad kids for next week okay like you
kick yourself and you say I'm stupid you
know then it's true okay that means your
house that's how to prove your husband's
right by the way okay
is to yell back okay now third choice
you remember okay you remember okay
then you come in the kitchen right you
open the door you put your arms up for
hug right and your husband says you're a
stupid then what do you do okay
does it not hurt it hurts okay it hurts
it still hurts okay I'm sorry but if
you're a really well-trained person and
that's the goal of everything we do is
to create well trained people mentally
well trained spiritually well trained
people if you're well trained to this to
hot
microphone too hot
maybe you're too hot maybe it's your
karma okay anyway if you're well-trained
and you come in the kitchen and the
husband says you're stupid
then what are you gonna do you see you
can adjust you can't calm stupid because
you're not stupid if you're stupid you
call him stupid and then your kids are
bad next week okay so you just have to
kind of smile and say okay honey and
there's a Buddhist practice you say huh
good I just used up a bad seed mm-hmm
call me stupid again
let me use him all up until he gets
tired you know then you're using up
seats a real Buddhist is like I get
copies dip it again yeah you know he's
doing okay so those are the three
options okay number five and by the way
these explanations came from six
different Lamas over a period of 1,300
years okay first one is 1700 years Vasa
Pandu second one was kamila Sheena third
one is Joanie lama fourth one is Jamyang
Sheba faithfulness $10 Amma from
Mongolia a lecture and the sixth one was
[Music]
coin short-tempered to me okay so I'm
giving you six different llamas in
history over 1700 years they each
explained this famous poem everyone
likes to explain this poem me too okay
so okay that's number five okay that's
an explanation of Maya okay that's an
explanation of illusion now let's go to
the next page page number six
it's called Aria Davis dog okay so Aria
David wrote a poem called four hundred
verses chatter Jataka and he lived about
seventeen hundred years ago eighteen
hundred years ago
and he calls it the dog okay he calls it
the dog he calls the illusion is the dog
and it gives two examples and we can do
it with Lucy is it Lucy we could do Popo
there they got two new cards we can do
with pop one Lucy okay
it means you you go like this okay and
then you go like this you take like a
rock okay
are you Davis says you use a rock and
you take a rock and you go and then the
cats like minions Troy and they run
after the rock okay then they go then
they look at you like they're supposed
to feel guilty right Michael feel guilty
because you tricked her you check the
cat or you tricked the dog that's called
our Ian Davis dog are you David wrote a
poem about this dog okay and he gave a
second example it's a mom who doesn't
have milk today
then she will stick her finger in the
baby's mouth the baby's like okay I
didn't have babies dis life but I I
heard about it and then they put a
finger in the mouth then the kids for a
moment the child is like hmm and then
they're like and nothing comes out okay
it's called unfulfilled expectations
okay
this is illusion okay illusion is all
about unfulfilled expectations in our
kitchen example what was the expectation
I'm gonna get a hug when I come in the
kitchen I will get a nice hug okay and
and our life is all about expectations
and those are an illusion why you don't
really know if you're gonna get a hug or
not do you okay let's be honest even if
you got a hug every night for a week
okay is there a possibility on the last
day of the week you won't get a hug yes
or no yeah
if you don't understand seeds you can
say definitely I'm not sure like I
expect a hug he gave me
- boots pizza last night he should be
happy you know probably I'll get a hug
but you have to say probably right you
have to say probably why because that's
life and you learned it when you were 2
years old I mean you were younger than
Francis when you found out you don't
always get what you want
okay and I accuse you of getting used to
it and accepting it as normal
okay uuk you know at a certain point my
brother killed himself when he was 19
okay he said this is stupid
this life is stupid and he went out in
the backyard and he shot himself in the
head okay and he said I can't live with
this this is crazy you know maybe you
get a hug maybe you don't get a hug I'm
tired of this you know so that was his
reaction the point is if you understand
seeds you can get a hug every night just
plant them what do you have to do to
your kids to get a hug from your husband
duh give them more hugs okay got it give
more of what you want don't let it be
maybe I get a hug okay just set it up
okay give lots of hugs you know this guy
in Norway he he told me he's gonna kiss
every girl in the in the restaurant I
said just calm down I don't mean it like
that you know but be friendly to
everybody you know who is appropriate to
hug give them lots of hugs okay give
Lucy hugs give Bobo hugs you can give
you grandma hugs
okay even your dad if he's okay I don't
know yeah or so late I don't know so
yeah look he's getting all these hugs
like there's I should get some hugs
anyway so what I'm saying is don't be
like are you Davis dog okay don't be
like that dog okay if maybe you run
after things you know you run after hugs
you get all excited
you know it's a rock okay you got it
life which is not planted consciously is
a rock okay running after money running
after hugs like a dog that somebody said
move and go like that you know and you
go oh I want that you know don't live
like that okay don't run after things
that you didn't plant just plant them
then they'll come to you okay then you
don't have to run out you see what I
mean
because when you run you can be
disappointed because life is an illusion
okay you're only it looks like you're
getting hugs because your husband wants
to give you a hug but that's not why
you're getting a hug you're getting a
hug because you gave a hug okay so plant
a lot of hugs okay and then there's no
rocks then you don't chase after rocks
okay all right Dave is talking about us
right how we live in a world of maybes
in a world of possible hugs okay Aryeh
Davis saying cut that stop that just ten
things then you get a hug on schedule
okay I'm not kidding okay it's a very
nice to have a partner that you designed
okay
it's very nice they do everything right
okay okay all right
number seven about illusion you know in
this example that we've been doing for
two days we've been talking about the
husband who was bad okay and then you
know we were analyzing why the husband
was bad to me okay and that's human
nature
okay when people go to the doctor and
the doctor says the tests came back you
have cancer you know everybody in their
mind or in their in their mouth they
will say why me why me
you know ripich I used to take me
upstairs for the lottery you know the
six million dollar lottery or something
my llama loved this thing and he would
say watch this lottery you know and they
will call somebody on the
telephone they say you just won six
million dollars and he said did you ever
hear one of them say why me
never okay when something bad happens
you're like why me
when you win the lottery you're like
it's me my you know people say my right
it's me okay so this is a tradition in
teaching the diamond cutter Sutra where
you encourage people not to only examine
their life when they have problems okay
you should examine your life when
something goes good you go home and you
get two hugs for free okay
then if you're a real thinker if you're
a natural philosopher you should say to
yourself why don't wait for something
bad to happen and say why me okay you
get two hugs going to bathroom and say
why me because you wanted to happen
again okay and this is a tradition when
you teach Maya the good things that
happen to you are also Maya okay
so understand okay don't just question
your life when bad things happen
question good
why do you meet Andy you know why this
beautiful man
intelligent etc you know handsome what
why then you should ask yourself why me
okay cuz you've got to keep it going
you see you've got to plant more seeds
you can't just meet a man and and use
him up you see this these will if you if
you just use them they will finish it's
like a debit card okay life is a big
debit card okay so when you get
something good in your lives to ask
yourself why me and it's because you
gave the same thing to somebody else you
help someone else get a beautiful
partner so you can't stop it's a pyramid
scheme
Karma's a pyramid scheme okay
number eight is depressing I don't like
to talk about it but it's part of Maya
okay
the normal experience of happiness or
pleasure than normal
experience of happiness or pleasure it's
like licking a razor blade honey on a
razor blade they call it in Buddhism
they call it honey on a razor blade okay
the normal way that people experience
the good things in their life is that
there are licking honey off of a razor
blade and they they don't feel the blade
because of the honey you see the mean so
most people when their kids are healthy
or the kids are smart or their business
is going well they just lick
they keep licking and they use it up
they use up the Karma and then
underneath there's a razor blade okay
it's a very terrible picture right I
don't like it probably he's gonna paint
it next week don't ya I know you're
gonna do that okay be careful because
under the things that are going right in
your life is a razor plane okay you are
using up seeds okay then you have to
replant them as you use them if you're
using these principles to make money you
have to share it after it comes you have
to share okay if you're using these
principles to to find a beautiful
partner you must help lonely people
you can't stop okay you must continue to
you and your partner should go to
nursing homes once a week seriously
okay if you want to have a long-term
relationship if you wanted to continue
then you and your partner should be
helping lonely people as a practice as a
Buddhist practice okay don't don't lick
razor blades okay
all right number nine this is a cool
thing about Maya okay remember we're
talking about illusion right there's a
you know the gadget programs like 20
years 25 years we debate every day for
three or four hours
it looks like wushu we are debating for
three or four hours every night
and it's hard it's really hard sometimes
all night and then you lose your voice
and people are screaming at you it's
kind of unpleasant a lot of people drop
out in the first few years like 50% and
then you know you just have to get used
to screaming and slapping your hands at
people and like this so it's 25 years of
really hard hard life you know the
monastery is not quiet meditative place
it's very stressful to be in the gash a
program and then we do meditate but then
everything else is stressful so then the
final day is very beautiful they dress
you up they hang all sorts of things off
you they hung this big bag off my belt
you know I said what's this this job
Luke what's Chubb low I don't know why
are you hanging it on me cuz guys she's
always have a chub Luke then some guy
told me I think it used to be a water
bottle but it's not anymore it's just a
heavy thing you have to hang on your
pants you know and I'm like okay and
they dress you up and they give you this
you got a picture of this get your hat I
know they give you this hat I was
talking to somebody today it probably
came from Greece they give you this
Gashi hat and and that day they give
it's like a Naval Academy you went to
the Naval Academy right
they give everybody this guess she had
even the non-gay she's good to have a
guy she had for like one hour you don't
get a degree in a Buddhist monster you
get a hat and that's your degree and you
wear it all the time so anyway on the
day that you do your final final exam
they give you a they give everybody the
Hat and then the you get examined for
three weeks day and night in my
monastery 1,300 monks examine you and at
the end the oldest mom comes up and he's
like any and he's supposed to ask you
the final question okay the final
question is is there an end to pain in
the
is it possible that in this world there
will be no pen in the future is it
possible you know he's like he's
supposed to ask you the same question
you know the last question after 25
years is always is it possible that pain
will end in the world for everybody no
and then you say yes and then
everybody's waiting you know and then
he'll say why you know and you say
because of Maya because what you see in
this world is a lie the world is a lie
all the pain in the world
it looks like it's coming this way but
it's not it's coming from you
you made all the wars in the world you
made all the disease in the world you
made all the starvation in the room and
you can stop it you know it's coming
from your sins right and then you say
and then everybody goes ah and they
throw that guess you had like a frisbee
and it's really beautiful and somebody
should make a a movie there's like a
thousand gushy hats flying through the
sky in the same moment you know then
they all fall down and it takes like two
hours to find your hat so the final - a
question is is there an end to pain and
they say yes because a lie stands on one
leg and the truth stands on two you see
sooner or later
illusion is always when you call
somebody sees that it's a thing you see
it's like Volkswagen diesel testing you
know now I mean sooner or later if it's
a lie somebody will notice you see
somebody will figured out that the
husband's coming from you you see it I
mean it for your whole life you're angry
at people who call you names right for
your whole life then you come to a pen
talk Frances teaches you the pen and
then suddenly the illusionist lies our
weak truth is strong if if they go one
on one for long enough
then then truth will will out truth will
win you see my Maya is always destroying
the nature of Maya is to be discovered
by intelligent people okay it's not
possible that this world will not become
a paradise okay because the pain the
worst hunger it all depends on Maya
you see people don't understand the
husband and everything depends on that
and when that starts to crumble
you know people come to this talk and
they tell their friends and suddenly
there's nobody yelling at their husband
right
basically war will finish okay hunger
will finish right it'll be amazing
the the inevitable future of this world
is is happiness okay because the
unhappiness depends on Maya
okay I'm not understanding what's going
on okay okay I'm gonna take a break you
got something he wants to do a pitch
yeah oh and then who's gonna go first
okay Steven McManus from the three
jewels let's give him a hand
thank you gosh whoa all right who wants
a free shirt and book what's the catch
if you sign up today for a membership we
are giving away free shirts and books
and as you may know or may not know
three jewels is dependent on our
community and everybody sponsoring it
we're a non-profit and we offer our
classes for free for 22 years all of our
dharma and meditation classes as is this
event now if we offer it for free we
always will offer them for free but we
depend on our community to support us so
if you sign up to become a member today
then we're giving away free shirt and
book and with a membership you get
discounted yoga classes you get
discounts on merchandise and
workshops and to get to be one of the
cool kids so if you sign up today there
there's a table out there they're
signing people up the other thing I want
to talk about is we're doing a retreat
we're doing a retreat in Nicaragua this
year with cocoa cocoa if you hear
stand-up coca Coco's completed a
three-year silent meditation retreat and
she'll be teaching with Hector Hector's
not here but as many of you know and
love him he's in China he'll be teaching
as well it's gonna be seven days of
silence in Nicaragua on a lake that used
to be an old volcano that imploded on
itself it's beautiful and that's going
to be in March all you have to do is put
in your deposit we have payment plans
available ask me or anybody that's from
Three Jewels about that that's March 10
to the 17th thank you and Tim so really
quickly I'm gonna be talking about three
events that we have coming up over in
the next couple months and at the end of
the year so the first one here is our
LOM REM retreat it's the Great Escape
this is a ten day residential retreat at
Diamond Mountain retreat center in the
pristine mountains of Arizona it's
really dry it's really warm and this
time of year it's actually really nice
to be out there and we have a the
program we've been doing this program
for about eight or nine years now and
it's an ongoing series everyone is
welcome to come and what's neat about
this program is it we have ten days
there and then in the middle of it we
have three days of silence so we guess
you Michael will teach for three days
then we'll go into silence for three
days and then come back for teachings so
you get an opportunity to integrate the
practices up in the retreat Valley in
your own cottages or shared rooms
depending which option you choose and
that's it it's a really it's it's been
an amazing program if we're getting more
more people coming so it actually sells
out really quickly the people from China
actually take up most of the spots so if
you're
interested and registering please head
to our website and following that
retreat and can you go to the next slide
please
is the five mysteries so what is that
it's the fifth installment of the
Comelec Sheila's series and maybe the
final one and I will see what happens so
I guess you'll be finishing up the come
unless Sheila teachings which is after
tonight's class you'll be then prepared
to move into the fifth of this series
and that's a different a little bit
different program that's a five day four
and a half day program where guess you
live will teach once a day and then
you'll spend the rest of the day inside
and practice up in the retreat Valley as
well so if you're interested in that
program please sign up and then finally
guess you'll have talked about a little
bit is we're gonna be starting our
teacher training in October so if you're
if you've have any inkling to learn how
to teach these courses how to get up on
stage or how to teach smaller groups the
ACI courses will be going through that
beginning in October so we're gonna have
a break are you gonna be signing so I
guess you'll will be signing books
outside there are cookies and
refreshments and beverages and bathrooms
so come back in ten minutes thank you
okay how does it go tareka Timmy ROM
Depot then people say Maya vishaya but
it's really two different words it's
Maya
and Allah Shia because there's a long a
so the next the next picture in the nine
is called a vishaya say of a Shia other
means down like a pond of value is the
down down word flowing wind or something
like that and she means to rest or to
lie down
it's there actually the root for scholar
because they sit all the time and other
words like that
so other Shia means that do that settles
on the grass in the early morning okay
it's called a vishaya in tibetan it's
Silla
okay Silla all right and there are 4
different explanations in the diamond
color Sutra of a Shia okay and it's on
page six this one and we talked about it
last night there's an ancient argument
are these nine images of impermanence
or are they images of illusion you see
because some of them are obviously
illusion like Maya okay and then some of
them are obviously impermanence like a
butter lamp like a candle life is a
candle you see so it has led people over
2,000 years time to argue
is this a teaching about impermanence or
is this a teaching about illusion or
emptiness you see so when you get to the
do this one's pretty obviously
impermanence okay the dude settles on
the grass then the Sun comes up and the
dew dries up and it doesn't stay okay so
one of the lamas vasa bamboo when he
explains the do he says nothing lasts
nothing less okay and it's sad I don't
even like to talk about it you know your
children aren't going to last you're not
going to last the apartments not going
to last your jobs not going to last
your relationships aren't going to last
your body won't last you know everything
passes okay
I like to do what's that song no your
clothes dad I doubt that
dust in the wind yeah everything passes
okay so this is about then I the the
llamas said number one it's a comfort
why when you're in the kitchen and the
husband's yelling okay a low-grade we
call it yesterday low-grade emptiness
okay a lower grade emptiness is the is
the absence of permanence you see so you
can if you can't remember the pen which
you should because I taught it every
time for a hundred years you can
remember just remember it won't last
forever you know when the husband's in a
bad mood it won't last forever I'm not
gonna say the lady's name or the country
because you'll figure it out but every
every year she used to come to Diamond
Mountain unhappy you know she's older
lady and every year she come unhappy and
I'd say what's going on she said my
husband's angry all the time you know
every year then one year she came she's
like so happy you know and she's so
relaxed you know and I'm like are you
okay and she's like yeah and their
husband had been ill you know I said
how's your husband he died then anyway
everything passes okay so at least maybe
you can hold your tongue in the kitchen
you know it won't last forever like
he'll get in a good mood someday or you
could be like that lady okay
you you know her I'm like I'll tell you
later then second one is it's a sadness
you know so it's a comfort that problems
in your life are also impermanent okay
they will pass there's no problem that
stayed forever it's not possible
actually okay secondly it's sad okay you
lose your partner you lose your children
you lose your house you lose your house
it's a sad thing okay
third thing but it's an opportunity okay
and I want to talk about the last line
in the sanskrit is mm - mm sanskrit um
okay even say even Josh Davian Sanskrit
um Ava means like that
okay very famous in Tantra a bomb it
means like that or even Maya shoot'em
that's I heard that's the opening line
of the diamond cutter Sutra so Ava means
like that okay - da VM you know from the
yoga Sutra right durst understood Genma
janma vena Nia what's that oh yeah yeah
things seeds you plant now will be
experienced veteran iya Durst 'or
understa seen in this life or not seen
in this my scene in the next night so -
tough young is the future tense it will
be seen okay mm - mm you should see such
Gotham so Sanskrit is the language Sun
means good kurta means made well well
designed sand skirt means well designed
winner M meatsac a in Sanskrit you have
to insert an S that's the rule and the M
changes to end like a hint or son Sahra
and you never ever say samsara or himsa
okay because M cannot come before air
since then in Sanskrit it's always son
skirt though so anyway kurta came into
English as create or cereal comes from
that in the days when C was K so
Sanskrit that means well put together
but what it means in the diamond cutter
Sutra and people always translate it is
anything produced by causes okay good
and can do nature picture is the
definition of Sanskrit oh right anybody
want to take a shot no kidding can do
nature picture the causes and conditions
some they come together and they kurta
things okay so it's very famous you know
people always talk about
oh the last verse of the diamond cutter
Sutra is talking about made things but
that's not the point okay that's not the
point the point is you're making things
okay they are made from your mind when
it says sans kurta and they're talking
about the saya of asana okay
it means seeds in your mind it's not
talking about things our main it means
you're making your husband your husband
is like a star your your husband is like
a scratch on your eye your husband is
like a lamp it's all about your husband
okay
or your wife okay or your husband or I
don't so it's it means that the whole
point of the last line of the diamond
cutter Sutra is you're making things
okay they're coming from you you're
making them and therefore those things
are passing they are they have to leave
like to do your body is being made by
your seats your husband's been made by
your seats
your children are being made by your
sins your your job is being made by New
York cities being made by your seats so
therefore it must pass away okay it's
like to do anything made by your seats
it's gonna pass away if you don't
understand see okay if you don't
understand seats okay and the cool thing
and the promise of the Buddha is that if
you understand seeds you can start
recycling you can start reinvesting your
seeds okay
seeds for money okay like you get money
then share some of it okay share 10
percent give away 10% that the Islam has
one of the pillars of Islam is zakat
give away 10% of your income and and
most good Muslims do it okay so give
away a certain part of your income why
cuz you plant new seeds and then the
income keeps coming you see so if that's
possible with money it's also possible
with your husband
you know if you want to keep them okay
keep keep visiting lonely people keep
serving lonely people okay this is how
the Karma this is how you make Karma for
a partner visit lonely people once a
week one hour then after it produces a
husband or a wife don't stop take him to
the nursing home you know every good
Buddhist who wants to have a partner
should be going to the nursing home once
a week okay or you're crazy because you
have to keep the seeds going okay sons
curtam here the last word of the diamond
color Sutra means things are being
produced by your seeds then keep going
don't let them just debit card okay your
life is a debit card and if you keep
using it you will end up with nothing it
will go to zero you see you have to keep
recharging it you have you know if you
understand the pen which Francis taught
then you're forced to keep doing nice
things for other people
you cannot stop okay because every time
you do a nice thing you get the result
and then it wears out okay so you must
okay that's the point of the first image
of the do other Shia okay of a Shia okay
second one partner hugs and children
hugs are particularly expensive seeds
and they are especially fragile okay one
of the most beautiful things about life
is to have a beautiful partner okay it's
one of the sweetest things in life if it
goes well why is everybody hungry for a
partner because it's the coolest thing
in life okay it's the nicest thing in
life if you have a good relationship
going with another person then it's the
sweetest thing in the life okay it
really is the sweetest thing in life
okay but it's expensive okay it's
karmically
very expensive okay and you know you
build up a lot of seeds then you meet
your partner okay the day you met your
partner you lost like ten thousand
karmak points okay and then how many
seeds per second 65 you know sit with
them quietly and watch TV for five
minutes you just used up three thousand
seeds you know don't do anything with
them you're you're using obscene okay so
if you understood this talk you can you
can play the system you can play the
system you know take your husband if you
like him or your wife and visit lonely
people with them and don't ever stop
okay recharge the seeds every week you
know it's like going to the gas station
karmic gas station okay if you have
something beautiful in your life and you
don't keep recharging the seeds you will
lose that thing for sure you will lose
that thing for sure mm - mm sensical
sanskrit um okay the last line that's
what it means okay all right so kids and
partners are very expensive karma okay
and you have to do things for other
people's children you have to if you
want to keep them such a nice young man
you have to invest in other people's
children or you will loose them okay
it's like that okay all right even Lexi
I count you're still you're a kid
because every when I knew you you're a
kid now you're a famous engineer but
that's okay number three the way that
karma opens you'd say you have a partner
okay you have a relationship the way it
opens is like a fountain okay like seeds
are you ever been the true vena Fountain
in Rome right it's all in the tourist
books and it's actually ugly and hard
and smelly but anyway there's this
famous fountain you know and people go
there throwing money people go at night
and take the money and you make a wish
and it has a shape right the fountain
has a shape but it's not static it's
it's moving it's new water every second
you know and but it has a shape like
this right like a mushroom or something
that shape is being maintained by a
constant flow of water it's never the
same water it's it's it looks solid
shape mushroom shape but it's really new
water every second your husband's the
same your partner's the same seeds are
flowing 65 per second and they're
creating the arms and legs and head of
Andy you know it's know these are
flowing out of your mind in a certain
configuration like the fountain so he
looks pretty much the same every day
when you wake up five but it's actually
flowing from your your mind okay so what
it says here don't expect stability in
your life okay it looks like he's the
same dad you had yesterday but he's not
he's a fountain and he can shut off
anytime or the fountain water can get
slow or fast mostly slow and no and your
dad will change you see that mean so
it's the nature of fountains to not flow
the same every day if you understand
that you can make a fountain which is
constant you see you can make a partner
who is beautiful forever okay oh gosh la
don't talk about forever you know
everybody knows life comes to an end
that's because people didn't understand
the temp debit card thing okay now in
your mind you're objecting you're saying
geshe-la the new york times which knows
everything more than the Buddha reported
never reported a person who didn't die
you know they have a obituary page they
don't have a deathless page you know
they never reported a person who didn't
die you know I I like you I enjoy your
talks I'm glad you came to New York I
hope you come back it's you're funny
if we get a free talk but don't you know
this stuff about living forever come on
the dogs had a meaning Oh around and
they one of them said you can use this
to write down messages and send to other
dogs you know and they're like no this
is a Chitauri
this is not a pen and that all dogs
agreed all the dogs in the audience say
no we never saw anybody use this as a
pen it can't be a pen okay
why didn't see as a pen they don't have
the C's okay so don't be like a dog who
says this cannot be a pen okay it can't
be a crime you just need a different
steep okay like don't say there's not
people around who didn't die opening
lines of the hatha yoga pradipika I
forget the deathless sages wander the
world in anonymously right nobody knows
okay because they're all got dog seats
okay got it
it's possible the person sitting next
years it's already a Buddha there's a
there's a tradition that every time
there's a Buddhist talk there's at least
one Buddha in the audience okay so we
don't know you can be what do you call
it
paranoid positive paranoia right it's
easier with the Karen family but okay
all right number four all right that's a
long story
the fourth meaning of do is Dharma
Quixote who was a great one logician
okay not a sexy Buddhist philosopher he
just talked about syllogisms and good
reasons and you know very dry very
difficult we study it every winter for
three months for 20 years it's dry
and he's like not Dharma cured he's dry
care D you know and so but he gets into
this weird conversation which kind of
answers the big question about the
diamond cutter Sutra isn't about
impermanence or is it about emptiness
and he says obviously they're connected
you know if you understand impermanence
you understand emptiness and you
understand pain so he connects the three
of them then he divides emptiness into -
okay so it's Mita
Daniel tomba dummy okay mr. chill Mita
dunya talked about Darkman these are the
four aspects of the first noble truth
okay these are the four aspects of the
first truth what's the first truth
suffering the Buddha connected them okay
Lord Buddha me that means things change
constantly like a fountain doing
ailments that cause you pain when they
change and don't but Dharma means
they're empty they are empty in two
different ways okay so what's the
connection
why did Buddha teach nine different
messages right they're supposed to be
secret messages I'm supposed to be
explaining them to you right the do is
obviously impermanence okay Maya
the last one is illusion emptiness okay
then what's the connection okay can you
that's like worth two hundred dollars
but no one's gonna get it right so
anyway in that kitchen okay in the
kitchen you have different things going
on okay
number one it's all impermanent okay why
it's flowing from your 65 a second seeds
what a dull it's changing every sixty
fifth of a second don't be surprised
when your husband's different the next
day it's like ten thousand seats later
okay yeah of course he's gonna be
different things change okay
do you know that's painful it's painful
when your husband changes you know I
he's not the man I married I married
this really nice guy who used to send me
flowers in chakra now he watches TV
yells that mean doesn't work you know
like change okay me thought then go
then what's the emptiness in the kitchen
Tim are Scott Tim thanks Francis I
always know you're gonna stay awake he
goes to bed early that's why he can not
fall asleep in the class not like some
people okay so yeah Tim never existed
the husband what do i what do I call him
what's the funny thing I call I need
three thing I need a spy yelling at me I
didn't do anything okay you're gonna you
think I'm being funny but I swear you're
gonna say it in the next 24 hours
I need to anything he's not yelling at
me I don't know okay that husband that
didn't do anything husband he doesn't
exist
got it that's emptiness he was never
there okay that's emptiness if you don't
understand it you will have pain okay
you will get upset all right got it and
anyway it's all changing comes it's
flowing out of seats at 65 per second
okay got it
that's why the diamond cutter Sutra
final words mix impermanence and
emptiness got it
you okay there Dominic Garrity says duh
obviously they're connected don't don't
try to button hold the Buddha when he
talks about impermanence he's talking
about emptiness when he talks about
emptiness he's talking about and
permanence obviously okay for him it's
like why are you asking this question
what's the final verse about emptiness
or impermanence yeah
bad question geshe-la both okay got it
because they're connected okay
all right next one is buh buh dum say
but budem somebody misread and many
years ago in our group and was calling
it boo doo dum which is which is dumb
okay
it's boot budem okay and it's
onomatopoeia $10 for anybody can get
onomatopoeia in censoring I'll give you
a clue it's a country okay forget that
Jambu jambudvipa right
what is jumbo it's the sound of a fruit
falling in the river
okay so there's words in English that
are like I don't know this is okay like
they they are what Babar barbaric yeah
the bird so anyway it's onomatopoeia but
but but but dumb this bubble okay it's a
bubble now all of the great writers are
like this ain't no normal bubble you
know or what kind of bubble is it it's
not a normal bubble
what do you mean normal bubble it's not
like an ocean bubble or a bathtub bubble
don't think that I'm like I'm sorry I
was thinking of bathtub bubbles you know
I was thinking of ocean bubbles because
I like to I like to surf you know so
someone tried to get me to go to
Indonesia I said I don't have time they
said it's worth a three days
certification I said I have time so
we're going anyway but Buddha doesn't it
means when the rain comes suddenly in
Arizona for example when it never rains
and then the rain the earth presents
itself to the sky and then rain falls
down from the clouds and then a little
bubble forms for a tiny second and then
explodes
that's but budem okay so all the authors
are like that's what real but put up
this is not a bathtub but Buddha okay
then they say look the point is not that
the bubble is impermanent that's not the
point
okay the point is that when a bubble
breaks it's a big windy calling it's
dramatic there's a bubble breaking okay
it took me a while to find on Google
right
that's the diamond color sutra good put
them okay and they say when bubbles
break in your life when relationships
break up it's not like buh it's like
everything explodes okay and that's the
first explanation of but budem in the
diamond cutter sutra when things mess up
it's an explosion it's not some kind of
quiet breakdown of your relationship
there's lots of screaming in the kitchen
and stuff like that okay
that's them first that's fossa bundu on
but budem okay hugs are not just do they
don't just fade away quietly okay they
explode like bubbles okay so we went
from of a Shia do the put put up and
there's okay and your relationship blew
up okay that's the point okay next one
hugs are not bubbles in the sea they
depend on fickle clouds and rain and an
earth to fall it means if you do get a
hug from your husband it's a lot of work
to create karmically
okay why there's three things you have
to create number one you gotta create a
husband number two you have to create
your own body number three you got to
get your body into the same kitchen as
your husband's body and then you got to
create an option between the two bodies
so it's difficult to get all those three
causes in the same room a husband who's
sorry you who are huggable your husband
who is hug a viable and then for the hug
to happen like it's like clouds and the
earth and the boat you see the bubble
depends on many things coming together
at the Sun scriptum many things have to
come together at the same time to get
one hug okay so they're expensive hugs
are expensive that's why you don't get
so many hugs okay number three bubbles
are made of water
before they come in the puddle the
puddle is water after the bubble forms
it's still water and then when it pops
it's still water drops of water going
around so the material the stuff is all
water but in Buddhism every part of the
hug you coming in the kitchen the
husband coming in the kitchen and you
know being close enough to have a hug
and he's not mad okay
those three things are like a bubble
because they're all the same water and -
and - Kamala gila it's all made of the
same stuff which is pain okay a hug is
pain and it's depressing okay
he says look hugs are pain okay all hugs
are pain all bubbles are water whether
they're forming or they're sitting there
or they're exploding they're all pain
you know a hug is just pain in a
different package you know then you're
like why are you so depressing come on
Sheila you know why can't you say
something nice about a hug he says think
about it you know number one when you
don't get a hug you feel upset right
number two when you do get a hug you
have to stop hugging at some point hugs
the beginning of a hug always kills the
hug okay once you start a hug you have
to let go
karma will separate you even if you
decide to hug Andy for 12 days or
something and you hook up some pbteen
still you're gonna have to let go some
day the start of a hug is the end of a
hug okay that's called so so far we have
dunya dunya give it away dunya what's
the third one
Kappa do check it do you know okay
it means it's the human condition the
human condition is to is to leave those
who would give you hugs the human
condition is that even if both
Hardee's want to stay together and they
want to give each other hugs
they can't karma will separate you okay
karma will tell your tear you apart this
is Calvin do chicky do you know the
human condition
you can't a normal person can't stop it
can a person who understands the pen
stop it yeah that's why we're here
okay we're not here to talk about how
painful is a hug okay we're talking
about eternal ha Gatien okay which is
called nirvana okay
Nirvana is not some stupid thing where
you're like in a refrigerator for the
rest of your life okay
it's endless hugs forever
okay and it's fun and it's cool and
you're designing hugs forever and it's
just a simple thing it's like brushing
your teeth you have to do it every day
you have to plant hugs every day okay
it's just like get up brush your teeth
give somebody a hug and then you'll
always have hugs
okay got it you don't have to lose your
partner to death or to something like
that okay if you understood where they
were coming from and you used what you
understood there's no reason why either
of you should die and there's no reason
why you should go it's not necessary
okay it's unnecessary there are whole
planets where people figured this out
we're called the back of this class
planet in Buddhist we are that stupid
ones in the back of the class we didn't
figure out the seed thing yet
we're still working for money and stuff
like that okay number four yeah that's
okay quarter wake up good seminar day
one I'm young ill my in court wake up
get Ximena what's a cup in in Tibetan
cop means needle
what's Galba cup rajagaha
okay
it's the it's the mountain where Buddha
taught the Heart Sutra okay it's called
the needle so anyway there's a famous
Sutra that says to live in this world is
to sit on a needle okay I don't know did
you ever put thumbtacks on your teachers
chair and in elementary school it's
great fun if you didn't do it then you
could start now and they jump up and
then you know and it's it's really fun
anyway according to Buddhism
you are always sitting on a needle to be
alive is to sit on a needle okay
and so when you and and and the number
four here says misunderstood hugs okay
hugs that you don't understand all right
that's like success that you don't
understand
why me you don't say why me okay you get
a hug and you're like yeah I should get
a hug I deserve a hug okay so that's
called a miss understood hug a Vidya hug
hug Asian okay you're getting a hug but
you don't understand why and it's
because you gave hugs in the past okay
if your husband's not giving you enough
hugs duh so give your kids more hugs
okay like that or somebody that it's not
inappropriate to hug them okay I want to
do one more we have to finish in like
one minute you gotta have my drawing
thing ready we'll go to the dream we're
not gonna finish tonight so I'll finish
next time I come okay and it's kind of
like fun but you have to remember where
we stopped so Steven McManus this is
your job I mean eventually it's up to
you I mean so the next one is called
Swapna Swapna and it means sleep supine
comes from hypnosis comes from that
and it means to sleep okay so Swapna and
it means a dream in the in the diamond
cutter Sutra it means a dream okay and
we can talk about that once you wake up
things in a dream are they're not quite
real right like I don't know if you have
a really good dream you wake up with
this stupid smile on your face and if
you're like me I like to not move it off
I like to like try to get back in the
dream you know like 1 out of 10 times it
works you know like I was dreaming and
some really beautiful thing with
happening and I'll just sit really quiet
and I'll try to fall asleep again and go
back to the same dream
I'd say once in a hundred times next to
me doesn't happen very often but in
general once you wake up the things you
saw in a dream are they don't mean so
much especially by the afternoon if you
have a hard day the sweet dream in the
morning is you forget it completely okay
and life is like that husbands who yell
at you or are like a dream okay they're
coming from your seats okay
then there's a school of Buddhism called
the Swatantra car right lower what lower
middle way okay and they have an
interesting thing they say dreams are
also real why can you guess they're also
coming from your seats
okay the content of your dreams is
coming from your seeds as much as the
content of your waking life okay you
know if you have really good seeds you
have dreams about flying or without our
airplane and that's supposed to be a
very good Buddhist dream things like
that okay and that's a reflection of
your morality if you have nice morality
you will have sweet dreams you see so
that's also coming from your seeds
okay so really life and dream is not so
much different okay
they're both flowing
from your seats okay your husband is
like a dream okay
he's flowing from the same seeds that
your dreams come from okay so it's a
waking dream or a sleeping dream but
they're all a dream okay and and ten
minutes after you wake up a dream is
it's not worth much you seen him in and
ten minutes after you walk out of the
kitchen and the hug is over you it's
just a memory and it memory is not warm
and you can't feel anybody's heart
beating or their tummy
and it's just like a drawing of a hug on
a piece of paper you know it's not a hug
it doesn't feel so good to look at a
drawing of a hug that you got it's you'd
rather have a hug right so that's all
he just says life is in that sense life
is like a dream one more let me see I
don't want to do lightning okay last one
I'll give you a free one this is there's
three more there's 12 in the color
chakra which is the secret teaching okay
and in the color chakra when they quote
the diamond cutter this verse there's an
extra line okay and it says John John
Yin and what's it called member and
Suqian there's a secret extra three so
I'm gonna give it to you for free okay
cuz you've been so nice number one it
means the cha cha do you know echo okay
life is like an echo okay and
anytime someone yells at you any time
someone says something hard to you it's
it's your voice from yesterday or the
day before okay everything people say to
you good or bad is literally an echo
okay so don't go blaming them okay they
are like a wall and you are yelling
yesterday
it's just slower than you expected and
the echo comes back okay so everything
people say to you in your life is you
it's just coming back okay so that's
color chakra number 10 in the color
chakra second one is called a gal main
which means this is weird you take a
sparkler and you go like this in the
dark or you take a torch and you you go
like this and it looks like a circle all
right with us
baton ladies in the Super Bowl I didn't
watch the Super Bowl it's like there's a
fire on the end of the stick and they
spin it really fast and then for a short
time it looks like a solid circle okay
and that's about the seats coming out of
your mind you see your mind is making 65
pictures per second they are not moving
it's just coming fast you see it's like
that fire if you spin it fast in the
dark it looks like a solid wheel it
looks like your husband's in the kitchen
it looks like your husband's yelling at
you
but it's not you see first moment second
moment third moment fourth moment if you
could slow things down you would never
get angry again if you could slow things
down you would never ever get angry if
you could watch Karma's opening in your
own mind you would never possibly get
angry okay and you can do that there
practice you can learn it at the three
jewels okay they're gonna teach it
they're lions dance right Singha virgin
Peeta in sanskrit the dance of the lion
and you should learn it okay it's a
practice that was taught by my trail in
the obvious Amaya Allan Connor they may
singing I'm game petting in synonym
shooting a tangent Elgin Lu Cheng Luke
turned on Lou me tomato patch a very
famous you can learn it okay
you can learn a meditation it slows down
the time and you can watch seeds opening
in your mind and then you will never get
upset at your husband okay because you
will see where the films coming from
okay
so that's called gyal me fire fire
circle that's the number 11 from the
colorchecker number 12 is called Suqian
Suqian means it's called chicken or
Suqian it means reflection in a mirror
okay that's the last one and we'll stop
there okay
reflection in a mirror means and we
talked about it last night as you go
through your day you have like 10% nice
things happen or you have 20% nice
things happen or you can even put a
number on it you know 38% today was good
gets lost 62 is not so good but that
percentage is exactly the percentage of
you of your personality okay so you can
count what happens in a day you can do
it every hour when the hour strikes
let's check if you're feeling good or
not okay or if things are going smooth
or not okay and it's gonna be twelve
chances right I mean 12 to 12 say check
it one o'clock check it to a clock check
at three o'clock are things going well
or not okay then make a percentage take
a ratio
I don't know 53% not so good geshe-la
53% the world was irritating to me
47% it was the world was pretty nice to
me guess what
that's exactly
personality by the percent you are 57%
irritating to other people you are 43%
nice to know you see that's the last
image of the diamond cutter Sutra the
secret version is that life is a mirror
a precise mirror the amount of
irritating people you meet is exactly
you okay yeah okay if you want to meet
more nice people then change the if you
go like this in the mirror Francis if
you like this in the mirror what do you
see you see the same thing come back
okay if you keep going around then life
will look like that okay and that's the
last part all right I owe you a little
bit from the middle right I owe you like
clouds a Brum Brum and what was the one
before that
oh yeah videoed I owe you videoed ok
we'll do it next time
now last thing we built a school we
built a college to teach these things we
teach teachers we have a shortage of
teachers you know we are in 35 countries
we have offices in 35 countries sorry 25
countries 35 cities and we have many
many teachers but we need many more
there are many countries asking for
teachers ok so we made a college we are
teaching teachers okay so we need you ok
the college is in Sedona it's three
times a year it's two weeks and we kill
you it's like 12 hours of work okay
and it's hard okay so we have two storey
building the bottom floor is torturing
teacher trainers trainees the top floor
is torturing translators so you can come
for either kind of torture
okay or Reid can you stand up
she's the beat the Dean of the college
she's the president of the college you
can you can talk to her but we have
we're very very stressed out
we're very we leave tomorrow we do I
don't know six countries in ten days and
we have many many many countries asking
for help for teachers so I Buddha said
every person in this room can be a
teacher okay
Buddhist have done you have what they
call Buddha Garba you have a seat every
human being in this room has a scene
inside to be a teacher okay so you know
I hope you will consider if you have
time talk talk to her
come and get trained and then go we need
we desperately need more people okay so
if you'd like to come sometime you're
very welcome the website is Sedona
College International Sedona College
International calm okay and there's a
new term coming up in May after that
September okay you work like a dog but
it's not like the other dog you get
great rewards okay so so please think
about coming sometime okay
and we really need people to give we can
teach you to give these kinds of talks
and there's no better life in the world
than to teach people how to get
everything they want you know there's no
happier life than to learn how to teach
that and share it with other people so
really encourage you too okay Sedona
College Internet okay see you next time
thank you and I'd like to thank Chisholm
and I'd like to thank Stephen and I'd
like to thank Tim and they work really
really hard they work all year they
stress about the money
there's distressing about the money and
I'd like to thing I also like to thank
all the VIP people who came today they
paid for a not a bad lunch but it wasn't
worth what you got charged but um they
paid I think ten thousand dollars for
this program so that we could hold it
for free so thank you very much please
come back soon again Michael Wilson
thank you so thank you all very much for
coming again I'd like to thank a few
more people we had an amazing group of
volunteers from the Three Jewels who
helped make this event possible so let's
thank them for all their hard work and
dedication
[Music]
I'd also like to thank our Diamond Club
members
we raised ten thousand five hundred
dollars today just help support this
event so thank you all very much for
your generous donations and overall with
with all the fundraising we raised
thirteen thousand seven hundred and
fifteen dollars for this event so give
yourself a round of applause for helping
support that and that really helps make
these events free for you this event
total cost twenty five thousand dollars
so 125 thousand fifty so thank you all
very much for your support to make this
possible and we hope to see you again
next year we have programs at the three
jewels all year long please come visit
us there and if you'd like to join any
of our retreats come to us at a station
Classics institute.org and we'll hope to
see you again next year thank you very
much for coming
[Applause]